<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE preface PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<preface>
  <title>Getting Started</title>

  <para><ulink url="http://docbook.org">DocBook</ulink> is an OASIS standard
  for XML that is ideal for writing long, technical documents that have
  complex structure and cross-references. With its semantic tagging, DocBook
  can be rendered as PDF for printing, HTML, <literal
  moreinfo="none">man</literal> pages, audio, or even Braille. This
  versatility and <phrase role="keep-together">reusability</phrase> make
  DocBook 4.5 XML the preferred format for <phrase
  role="keep-together">O’Reilly</phrase> books.</para>

  <para id="getting_started">Not only does this document explain how to start
  writing in DocBook, but it was created using the same markup and toolchain
  used for a typical O’Reilly book, so you can treat it as a model for your
  own manuscript. <xref linkend="docbook_xml_markup_guidelines" /> contains
  information about markup.</para>

  <note>
    <para>This document exists in two PDF forms: a print-friendly version
    (<filename>docbookguidelines_print.pdf</filename>), which displays URLs in
    parentheses after links, and a web-friendly version
    (<filename>docbookguidelines_web.pdf</filename>), which displays links in
    blue and hides the URLs. Please be aware that if you print out the
    web-friendly version, you may not be able to tell where the links are. See
    <xref linkend="web_pdfs" /> and <xref linkend="inserting_hyperlinks" />
    for more about web versus print PDFs.</para>
  </note>

  <sect1>
    <title>Why DocBook?</title>

    <para>Why not troff? Why not LaTeX?</para>

    <para>We’ve got nothing against LaTeX, troff, or any other formatting
    markup system. But typesetting markup like LaTeX is inherently focused on
    formatting—font size, margins, alignment, etc. We’d rather you spend your
    time focused on the semantic structure of your book (how sections are
    divided, which information goes in a sidebar versus a note, and so on),
    and that’s where DocBook shines. In the same way most well-designed
    websites separate content from formatting using XHTML and CSS (XHTML for
    the content, and CSS for the formatting), DocBook lets us abstract
    formatting decisions away from content decisions.</para>

    <?dbfo-need height=”1in”
?>

    <para>Particularly as O’Reilly expands its efforts to provide content in
    multiple formats and at multiple stages of the content’s life cycle,
    cost-effectively generating multiple, distinct output formats from the
    same source document becomes critical, even though it means losing some
    degree of granular control over the output.</para>

    <para>What does that mean for your book? It means that you’ll be able to
    view drafts of your book throughout the authoring process that are
    formatted much as they will be for print, and it means once your book is
    finished, it will go live almost immediately on <ulink
    url="http://my.safaribooksonline.com/?portal=oreilly">Safari Books
    Online</ulink> and other digital and ebook retail channels, rather than
    needing to first be converted into DocBook from another format, which can
    take a week or longer.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>For More Information on DocBook</title>

    <para>This guide is tailored specifically to help authors get the most out
    of O’Reilly’s DocBook authoring toolchain. For more general information,
    see Norm Walsh’s <ulink
    url="http://www.docbook.org/tdg/en/html/docbook.html">DocBook: The
    Definitive Guide</ulink>, an excellent online reference for DocBook
    XML.<footnote>
        <para>Although we’re publishing <citetitle><ulink
        role="orm:hideurl:ital"
        url="http://oreilly.com/catalog/9780596805012">DocBook 5: The
        Definitive Guide</ulink></citetitle> any minute now, we’re sticking
        with DocBook 4.5 for the foreseeable future.</para>
      </footnote> You’ll find <ulink role="orm:hideurl"
    url="http://www.docbook.org/tdg/en/html/part2.html">reference
    pages</ulink> for every DocBook element, including its content model, a
    description of its purpose, a list of parents that can contain the element
    and children that can be nested in the element, and the attributes the
    element takes. Other resources that may be helpful include:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><ulink url="http://www.docbook.org/">DocBook.org</ulink></para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><ulink
        url="http://www.dpawson.co.uk/docbook/reference.html">DocBook Basics
        and References</ulink></para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><ulink
        url="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">The
        DocBook DTD</ulink></para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><ulink
        url="http://www.sagehill.net/docbookxsl/index.html">DocBook XSL: The
        Complete Guide</ulink></para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect1>
</preface>